<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The British bell-man</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77552</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99864153</idno>
  <idno type="VID">116375</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240909526</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4823</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E442_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204688</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99864153</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99864153e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77552)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116375)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 70:E442[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The British bell-man</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year of the saints fear. Anno Domini, 1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A Royalist pamphlet-- Thomason catalogue.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary order to print.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 12. London".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:116375:1"/>
            <p>ORdered that a competent number of these bookes be forthwith printed, for the service of the King and Kingdome; and be dispersed through all Counties, Cities, Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughes, and Towns Corporate, and all other market Towns whatsoever, within this Realme of <hi>England,</hi> and dominion of <hi>Wales:</hi> and that all who love their King and Countrey, and hate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion and Treason, doe forthwith make all provision and speed that may be to rise, and take by force or otherwise, all Garrisons they can in all parts of the Kingdome, and summon in the Countrey to them, for the speedier suppression of these <hi>abominable malicious Rebels, and Traitors, this prevailing Party in the Parliament Houses,</hi> and their Army, who by wicked craft and subtlety, have undone three flourishing Kingdomes already, and yet would againe engage us in another warre with our brethren of <hi>Scotland:</hi> It is also desired that our brethren of the Association, would keep their men in the field, and when <hi>Cromwell</hi> is gone for <hi>Wales,</hi> fall upon the other part of the army remaining in the Countrey neere us, with all the power of horse and foot they can make, and we will endeavour in the City to second them to the utmost of our power: now is the time for us to free our selves from slavery, and put an end unto taxations; we shall never have a settlement else.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116375:1"/>
            <p>THE BRITISH Bell-man.</p>
            <l>Printed in the Year</l>
            <l>Of the Saints fear.</l>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Domini,</hi> 1648.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:116375:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116375:2"/>
            <head>The British BELL-MAN.</head>
            <p>O Yes, O Yes, If any one can give me notice of four great Ships laden with Money, lately at <hi>Gravesend,</hi> to be passed without Search, by Ordinance of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and can helpe to take them, he shall be well paid for his paines, and have many thankes.</p>
            <p>O yes, O yes, If there be any more Fools or Knaves will go soul and body to the Divil for an heretical, persidious piece of a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> Incendiaries, Boutiseu's, Faus of Faction and Sedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, with brazen Faces and feared Consciences, having nothing but Perjury &amp; Lyes in their Mouths, Falshoods, Treasons, &amp; Mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religions in their hearts, dayly Murders, Roberies and Oppressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in their Actions; Let them repair to the red-nos'd Rebell, Thieftenant <hi>Oliver,</hi> or his blacke General <hi>Tom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who helpes to disthrone the King, to change Monarchichal Government, to subvert the Protestant Religion, and Lawes of our Land, to cry down Presbytery, and Crown, the Kinglings, the Bussones, the Mountebanks of <hi>Westminster.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who saves the lordly Lurdanes (after seven yeares misrule, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing of the Kingdom, imprisonng and abusing of the King, and suffering <hi>Haman</hi> to strike him) from taking leave of their Allies at <hi>Tower-hill</hi> and <hi>Tyburne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O yes, who sacrifices the City and Countrey another seven yeares to their insatiable avarice?</p>
            <p>Who helps them to pill and poll them by their ravenous Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements (the Committees and their Substitutes) for more Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to send beyond Sea?</p>
            <p>O yes, Who buyes Bishops, Malignants Lands? Who buyes <hi>Pauls</hi> Steeple? Who buyes the Kings cast shooes and boots? Who buyes his Guards Coats? Who buyes Sun and Moon?</p>
            <p>O yes, Who sends them thankes for their Ordinance for forc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing taxations for their four last Bills and Declaration against the King.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:116375:3"/>
            <p> Who beats the Boyes from Catsapellet and Stool ball? Who sights with <hi>Poyer,</hi> with the Lord <hi>Iuchrquin,</hi> with Colonel <hi>Iones</hi> of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and our Brethren of <hi>Scotland?</hi> Who? and they shall have new Snap-sacks in hand, blew Bonnets, and Capon tailes, when the <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Welch</hi> be conquared, Promises enough for present, and as much Pay at last as those that have been turned off with nothing.</p>
            <p>In the beginning of this Hell-spew'd Sessions, we had as large Promises of happy Accrewments unto this Church and Nation as subtle Treason could in slie and specious Language possibly suggest. We had them usher'd in with a <hi>Protestation</hi> in the first place; in which our Religion, our Lawes, our Kings Honour, his <hi>Parliaments</hi> Priviledges, our own Liberties and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties were the common Theames. We had them waited upon with an Oath after the a Covenant, which neverthelesse were only to be as the passages at which <hi>Jephthaes</hi> Souldiers tried the lisping <hi>Ephramites</hi> in their <hi>Sibboleth,</hi> witnesses your Answer of the 26<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>May,</hi> 1646. unto our <hi>City Remonstrance</hi> in the latter end of <hi>p.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>We had many Pamphlets commended dayly unto us, <hi>The inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity of a Parliament, how that it could have no sinister end,</hi> as if a Multitude could be void of Knaves to contrive, and of Fooles to concurre in Mischief. Many Plots were discovered dayly against our Religion and our Lawes, in which ye <hi>Machiavils of West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minster,</hi> ye <hi>Malevolo's</hi> might have claimed the chiefest Livery, as <hi>Beelzebubs</hi> nearest Attendants in that kinde: but they must be fathered still upon our old Iusticers, (and indeed they can do lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, that cannot bely an Enemy, ye thought it best to cry Whore first) that in them you might be little and little undermine our King and Vs,; and sacrifice our Religion, our Lawes, our goods, our Lives and Liberties, yea, our very Soules too (for ye have silencenced almost all our able Guides, and daily burne their Escripts) unto your own boundlesse Lusts, Ambition, Pride, Covetousnesse, and Pleasure. These were the Originals, the Springs of your after-acted Villanies; not that candor and zeal so often dissembled in your glossie <hi>Declarations.</hi> It is now suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently manifest by your Actions, the truest Interpreters of mens intentions. How would you have us thinke you really intend as you pretended, when the courses you run conduce to the very contrary ends. Whilest the King and his Faithfuls retained their Places of Dominion, we enjoyed such golden Dayes of Peace
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116375:3"/>and plenty as we must never see againe so long as you Harpyes you sucking purse beeches and your implements be our Masters:</p>
            <p>Were we not enough damnified with your souldiers during the time of the warre, but you must still burden us with them now 'tis ended? Did not Taxations then light heavie enough upon us, but you must continue them still? How could you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume more then twenty millions of money upon such slender ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in so few yeares? The Souldiers have had little else save bread and cheese, which have come from the Countrey over and above those vast summes: ôh your Coffers be not yet full enough; Some of your munkey brats be not yet provided for; but hye you hence 'tis best you Irchins, you Caterpillers of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, to <hi>New-England</hi> and the <hi>Spaw,</hi> after our gold you have sent away, lost on a sudden we send you to <hi>Styx</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a penny in your mouthes to pay your passage to your God <hi>Pluto:</hi> Our brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Inchequeen</hi> will finde you more worke then the boyes in <hi>Moore-fields</hi> and <hi>Strand:</hi> Your goodly glozings and rabble-serving Collusions have been but like water-men upon <hi>Thames,</hi> looking one way and rowing another; and now you see your holy Cause will not succeed by opposition, you come up, and would cloze (since Money will not work upon our brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi>) with our City in the Presbyterian Government, in the restitution of the <hi>Militia</hi> and Tower; but for the Protestant Religion, and our old Rubricke, you still wave them.</p>
            <p>I pray you let me aske your honesties a question? Could <hi>Say</hi> and his Confederates have their nocturnall meetings so frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not have some treasonable Designes, which the rest of the Houses and our selves might not be privie to: We may see now the reason of your Bill, to sit as long as you listed; we trust<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (such rare men were you in leading our faith and belief so in a string) the ground thereof had been the redressing of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny grievances of the Kingdome, and transaction of the Irish af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires as was pretended; but it proves otherwise; That, which (had you been honest) would have made this Nation the happiest under Heaven, you have made the bane and ruine of all good people: You have demeaned your selves meet, as an aged Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman said of you, when he heard the King had signed you that Bill; You would (said he) grow so ambitious that you would set all the Kingdom on fire; and when once you had got Your fingers
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116375:4"/>into its purse, you would become so insatiately covetous, that you would never seek the settlement of peace; whether this man guessed aright or no, let any who hath his five Senses judge.</p>
            <p>We likewise call to minde your other Bill for his Majesties referring the choyce of his Privie-Counsell unto you (colour'd by your out-cries against those his old faithfulls) and your disho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest proceedings against them; your framing scandalous Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons amongst your selves, and sending them abroad for hands; a notable way to worke upon exasperated minds, and to exaspe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate mindes to work upon against them; but a way which may destroy any innocent man: While the Shepherd had his dogs, you Wolves could not raven his flocks; but since you supplant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, what prank you and your Creatures, your Substitutes have playde, we have seen and felt; and you or they, or all of you, may one day answer for; We may say now, as no King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or State ever yet could, scarce one honest man in Office amongst us; but no marvaile: We know the Proverb, <hi>like Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters like men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh but we wrong you, you are speciall Patriotes: 'tis you, Presbyterians may be no further trusted; you be the honesties, there is no nay: and take it as granted, though nothing more questioned or so questionable: We thought your exclusion of Bishops out of the upper House, and bedaubing them with the goodly habiliments of Arminiannme and Popery, had been for some other end than that for which you expulsed the eleven Members; to paucifie the number of those you conceived would countervote you, that you might easilyer doe what you lusted, and lead the left shallowlings <hi>volens volens</hi> in the trace of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse; and that you might unquestioned <hi>adhinnire</hi> after fresh Maiden-heads and neighbours beds; Ill courses cannot endure good Discipline; for this very cause, had the Prophets and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of old, Nay, our blessed Saviour and his Apostles, lived here in <hi>England</hi> in these dayes, they had certainly been made new Papists by this <hi>Quintescence of villany</hi> this wicked piece of a Parliament and their hellish helpers: We thought your Votes against pluralities had been for promotion of the Gospel, not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vision of the Clergy; and to make the <hi>wiseakers, the looke like geese,</hi> the naughty part of them (that will be any thing for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, <hi>omnium horarnm homines</hi>) for you: neither did wee till now of late imagine your possessing your selves of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116375:4"/>Shipping and <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> Ports (so finely shadowed with the remembrance of the late spoiled <hi>Spanish</hi> Fleet, and your Disres of the Kingdomes safety) had been the Prologue to this tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Tragedy you have since acted; much lesse our selves should be the last Scene thereof: yet herein wo must needs ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge Heaven just in our punishment: for it was we <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> that enabled you to your impious illegal courses of slaughter, Plunder and Sequestration (contrary to the known Lawes of this Land, your selves know it very well) against the King and his Survants: who (I am now perswaded in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>science) being farther discerhing than our selves, aimed at nothing but bringing you to the trial of the Law for your Treasons, that we might enjoy the benefit of the Lawes of our Land, and the Protestant Religion, as it stood established by our Law: God forgive us our amisnesses.</p>
            <p>I pray you, If a man might aske your high and mightinesses a question, What meant you displucing of the Eurle of <hi>Essen,</hi> and your after poysonling him? (for 'tis certain you did so, many of us know it, deny it as much as you will) and your putting of your Scoundrel Army and their Mechanidke Captaines under the command of <hi>Fairfax</hi> and <hi>Cromwell,</hi> two atheistical <hi>Independents?</hi> What meant your late force done upon our City and the eleven Members; your displacing and imprisoning our Lord Maior and Aldermen? For it was you that went away to the Army that for on them, though now you say, you knew nothing of the last Plot: Had those that were Cavalietish plaied us such trickes of <hi>Leger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de-main,</hi> we would have cast in their teeth: what not?</p>
            <p>But you (or dear Brethren) are men of another stamp; yet hard to say, <hi>Whether Barrell better Herring,</hi> I hope you did it out of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity, with a good, charitable, pure intent, to promote and set forward the holy Cause. You would sain say something for your selves, but I know not what, You meant well, <hi>But the Ape hath discavered himselfe to be so by cracking of Nuts.</hi> Thus doth Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, Ambition, and indiscrcet zeal make many men loose their wits they know not where. Indeed such tricks befit well your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent Cause: not to be promoted but by collusion: but your transported fawcy Spirits may haply in the end be taught to be more submisse and sparing in abusing them from whom you had your power. You would sain come off with us now, but stay a little, good Mr. <hi>Musties,</hi> You thought it easie to enslave us <hi>English</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:116375:5"/>to strangle in the birth our Classicall Projects, our Consitorial Practices, and Con<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>l Designes of zealous Brethren in the Land: such Illuminates you counted us: you sure thought our braines made of the pap of an Apple, and our hearts of Aspen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaves: Religion (which should be the Rule) must be onely a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult</hi> of policy, a stalking Horse to catch Fooles, and be pretended onely to serve <hi>Bakylonian</hi> turnes. But go you serve <hi>Baal</hi> and <hi>Ash<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teroth,</hi> if ye like it; we will no popular Cantonings of dismem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred Scripture; none of your Missives prophetical Determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in their heretical Conventicles. We will not build our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation upon the facing impudence of such light skirts, such hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish Impostours: let the Truth they teach, and your <hi>Parliamentary</hi> Proceeding come to scanning, the <hi>Turkish Alkaron,</hi> and <hi>Cades,</hi> and <hi>Kets,</hi> and <hi>Piercies</hi> and <hi>Nevils</hi> Actions will be as warrantable, as sutable with the Word of God and Law of this Land. Though you have ecclysped the Lampe of Light, you must not thinke us as Geese, which (when they are driven on by night, and a long staffe held over them) will go without noise or reluctancy holding down their heads? We Protestants are not so crest, fallen, as that we shall go on as you Independents would dispose us; if you gifted men with their new learning (for old they have none) can teach us more than yet we know, or you with your new policy can contrive us better Lawes than those we have, we will yield, and thanks them for such instructions, you for such legislati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. I beseech you, Will your Wisedomes or common Sense, or understanding, or what you will call it, approve of nothing in our <hi>Common Prayer Book,</hi> that you present us with an <hi>Inane nihil,</hi> a new <hi>Directery</hi> of a noddy Synod: or finde you so many defici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies in Monarchical Government, that you should look to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce an <hi>Ochlocracy, a People Sway.</hi> You know the King can do no wrong: and we know that by Him we had redresse (which very few could obtain from you or your Officers) of wrongs: Why then sought you to depole Him, and to change the Regal Government? O, it was to crown your Selves and undo Vs. But bear ye, <hi>Sequitur superbos ultor à terga Deus,</hi> If you believe there is one, <hi>Pride will have a fall.</hi> Lo, even the very touching of the Crown hath already crushed you, hath made the People every where forsake you, and all the wiles and flatteries in your bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomes will not regain them, Would you not give the Maker leave to dispose of his Creature? Shall not be governe by what
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116375:5"/>Substitutes he pleases, but they must be supplanted by you? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, ye misborne Elves of <hi>Lucifer,</hi> your implous Actions; in this very thing ye joyn your selves unto <hi>Apollyan,</hi> ye encampe against God that made you; and know asuredly, that <hi>Though ye may escape punishmant in this Life, ye must die, and rise, and come to judgement:</hi> but we hope our, Brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> will shaw ye the Suburbs of Hell in this World. Our People see enough now your jugglings, and how, you turne Catith Pa<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and shift off things from your selves to your Army. Yet while ye seemed to look and run two several wayes, and now ye do so again; but like <hi>Sampsons</hi> Foxes ye joyned together in the tail. We observed how that the Army (when the Kingdom murmured at the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prisal of the City) professed herselves your Servants, and your carriage of those businesses, and that you and the Heads of your Army, have since taken an Oath to live and die together: and that you shift off the Imprisonment of our Lord Maior and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen from yourselves to <hi>Fairfax,</hi> and he to you again; but they must lie in Prison howsoever, they must not be restored unto their Places. I pray ye, Whose hands then still the <hi>Militia</hi> and Tower be in if they be restored, <hi>Prechyterians</hi> or <hi>Independents?</hi> Take notice my Fellow Citizens of this slurre, If we should assist them in another Warre, we should again be bassled and muffled by them.</p>
            <p>We remember that Ordinance of yours in or about <hi>August</hi> last wherein you threaten Imprisonment, Plunder, and slaughter by <hi>Fairfax</hi> and his Army unto those that shall refuse to pay any your illegal (and now that the Warre is ended, unnecessary) Impositi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, by way of Excise, Loane, Myzes, Weekly and Monethly Assesments: though to go after the rest of Leavies, the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of your selves and implements, and your Brats, not pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Service of the Kingdom. I pray you, may I aske your Knaveships (neither better nor worse, but even so) how stands that Ordinance with our Liberties and Properties, the two wonted Sonnes of your former Declarations? and you have the other Week stopt the payment of <hi>Debentures,</hi> and <hi>Pensions</hi> to those that have lost their Limbs and Husbands in your Service, to let us see which way our Monies must go: and your Souldiers what they shall have at last from you.</p>
            <p>We guesse the reason of your sending away the King to the Isle of <hi>Wight;</hi> the peoples hearts were too much hazarded when he
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116375:6"/>was neere; your selves and your taxations could not be long enough liv'd; You feared Petitions, &amp; impeachments, if he should get power to call you to his Barre, and that your accounts should be reviewed: You have carryed your selves well in your places the while, have you not? Or thought you to tutor him with a bit and a bob into observance of you, as men doe apes? when you had him there, and much up in a stinking new built roome under severs looks, and made him his own scussion when his fire wanted repaire, and <hi>Haman</hi> bestowed some bussets on him, and all appearance of succour kept from him: you thought he would for his enlargement doe any thing; but know you, we take notice what it was you would have had him done, and or these your subtle wayesed being it to passe: that which you so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited him for was the signing of the foure Bils, whreh had been (if you could have forc't it stom him) the utter ruine of us all, and of our posterity after us: you would have brought us into worse condition than Turkish slaves; you would have had more power from the King to abuse (now you have a Ras<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call army <gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to enforce) than himselfe, or any of his Predecessors had to use over this free-borne Nation; What <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dec<gap reason="illegible: blotted" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies</hi> would not have bowed to you, or who ever should im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach you of evill, should have been straight way made more mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable than <hi>Job:</hi> the <hi>Sabaans</hi> your Committees should fall upon his oxen, his Cowes and sheep, your Sequestrators should fall upon his rents, and the <hi>Caldeans</hi> should fall upon his Campels, your Troopes should fall upon his horses, and you your selves would ssterve him in prison, you would finde some publick use for his private estate: We thanke you heartily for your good pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects; Be these they you have been this seven yeares in hatching? If the King had signed you those bils, how should any man make his will, and barre you from being his Executors? but we hope God in his due time will release us, and pay you the wages of your wicked wayes: our Kings suffering for us, shall for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teach us our duty better towards him: We know what of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers of gracious Acts he hath from time to time proposed; but because they were conducing to our good, not your ambition and avarice, therefore you refused them, and say they were not fit for you to receive: We think yet upon your late Declaration against him, when you had before hand traduced him all ouer the Countries, by you miscreant imps of the father of lies, (troop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116375:6"/>independents) as guilty of his late Fathers death, and shut him up, not giving him leave to answer it, or so much as notice of it; but bidding <hi>Haman</hi> tell him you would trye him for his life; This was an honest part in you, was it not? yes, like as honest as your other dealings; you drew low upon the lees of Malice, when you had nothing left but a recapitulation of former lies and slanders: you shall have thanks for it, yes marry shall yee: Send again your Petitions to <hi>Taunton. Deane</hi> in <hi>Sommer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>setshier,</hi> and <hi>Rumford</hi> in <hi>Essex,</hi> or some whether else: happily some body may thanke you now: Will you take my counsell, and thanke one another, so shall you not goe without thankes: You Rake-shames, hot burning coales be your portions; when you deale so basesly and so treacherously with your King; What Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice may your fellow-subjects (a little while your slaves) looke for from you; But what may men expect from impudence and wickednesse in the <hi>abstracts;</hi> from men (doe I say men) from Devils, from things worse than Devils, so often guilty of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury, murder, robbery, oppression, and treason? You cursed <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffes,</hi> how suits this with the Law of God or of the Land, with your Protestation and your Covenant? You would seeme to al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge many reasons for that Declaration: but those that moved you thereto were much otherwise than those you lay downe; they were the finall accomplishment of your first intended treasons: the exterpation of Monarchichall Government, the Coronation of your selves, &amp; our slavery, which to bring about (now that you had lost your selves in our opinions) you devised this recapitulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of your pristine forgeries, with which you had somerly befool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us all: Confiding it would put out of our memories the late Seales of your <hi>Legerd dermaine</hi> dealings, and reprint in us those jealousies and disaffections towards our gracious Soveraigne, which in severall they did before: but stay, since he chooseth ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to endure your disconsolate prison, than passe you such Bils as may be ours and our childrens mine, you must (rake you hell for lyes, and skum the Devils) never more look againe to divide our hearts from him: you have discovered your selves too farre to regaine any interest in our affections: wee would enjoy our Religion and our Lawes, which we must not look to doe, till we get you to the block and gallowes: When we looked for a settlement of our King and Kingdome, Loe you false your words and break Covenant with our brethren of <hi>Scotland:</hi> you
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116375:7"/>provide Armes and Snap-sackes, and prepare for more Warres: Never were <hi>Rake-hels, Buffoones, Rebells, Vermine,</hi> so desperately set to undo their own native Soil, and Church in which they were baptized; but we know the reason, Yelive to well, Ye fare to full (Ye can have your Feasts each day of all the dainty Cates our <hi>City Cookery</hi> can devise) Ye grow too fat in bag and bodie, <hi>by fishing in troubled waters to desire Peace:</hi> neither regard ye the empty Purses and hungry Bellies that ye have made in the City, especially since your lurching it out of the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> command. Ye may see if ye would (but ye will not) multitudes of thousands (who formerly had Trading and Worke enough for subsistency) now sit hunger-sterved in chimney-corners without imployment to get them bread. Ye know that since ye took the Tower and <hi>Militia</hi> from us, and sent away our King, the <hi>City</hi> hath had no Trading, and yet Ye send not for him home, but Ye can send for your Taxations, as if our Trade were good. Ye have made this famous <hi>City</hi> of <hi>London</hi> not onely poor but the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Scorne and Mocke of all the World, by your force done upon it in <hi>August;</hi> and as if Ye had not then enough wronged our streets with a handfull of your scummie Armie; and in derision as Ye passed along, bid us <hi>Go buy more Swords for our Apprentices.</hi> Had ye not meddled in the businesse, but made nse of us, we could have ruled them without slaughter, and would; but so ye may peer it, Ye weigh not our dishonour nor their bloud.</p>
            <p>I may seem a new <hi>Britannicus</hi> for thus phrasing you, but it was ever held lawfull <hi>to call a Spade a Spade,</hi> it is good to uncase such Imps that they may be known what they be, it is good to disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver such <hi>Pauthers,</hi> least when you have allured more with the sweet scent and party-colourednesse of skin (I mean your calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies against our Friends, and your sugared Declarations) you as those Beasts prey upon them with bloudy Tallens, as aheady you have done upon us, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> gave not <hi>Elimas</hi> any gentle termes, nor did Saint <hi>Peter</hi> speak Butter and Honie to <hi>Simon Magus;</hi> our Saviour himselfe (that Man of meeknesse) called <hi>Herod a Fox,</hi> and <hi>Iudas a Devil,</hi> when they deserved it. Since ye aime not at Peace, but make it your <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> your whole endeavour, your special studie day and night, by all kinde of iniquitie to keep Faction and Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition on foot, and maintain opposition even where it needs not, Ye are to be curried in your kinde, and rubb'd as ye deserve; not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116375:7"/>to be smoothed or sleeked over, least ye please your selves too well in your impierie, and our oppression never have redresse. Ye talked much in the beginning of your Sessions, that ye would open Obstructions of Law, <hi>not stop the course of justice and equity:</hi> but hear a little your own falshood, and go chew the cud, as when ye receive Letters from <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Give us leave to let our Neighbours understand the Suites late in <hi>Chancery</hi> betwixt one <hi>Wilkes</hi> and one <hi>Dutton</hi> of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood of <hi>Nantwich</hi> in <hi>Cheshire,</hi> and two Knaves <hi>providers, of your Independent Faction</hi> there, one <hi>Becket</hi> and one <hi>Gellicorse:</hi> The businesse was thus, <hi>Wilkes</hi> and <hi>Dutton</hi> (good honest <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians</hi>) had much Cattell and Cheese taken from them In the time of the Warre <hi>by Becket</hi> and <hi>Gellicorse,</hi> without any Order from the Councel or War there; and the goods not converted to the use of the Publique (as was pretended) but imbezelled by the two <hi>providores:</hi> now (since that the Courts were opened) <hi>Wilkes</hi> and <hi>Dutton</hi> repair to the <hi>Chancery</hi> for Reliefe, the <hi>Exchequer</hi> at <hi>Chester</hi> being not as then open, or not daring to meddle with any of yours for fear of a snub, and <hi>Becket</hi> (for himselfe and <hi>Gellicorse</hi>) hasteth to Sir <hi>William Brereton, goodly</hi> Sir <hi>William Brereton,</hi> who forth with makes Relation of the matter unto You his Brethren of the two Houses; and you (all of you apprehensive enough of what might betide your selves and your honest Committes as well as the <hi>providores,</hi> if such Suites had audience) presently di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spatch a private Ordinance unto all the Courts then open in the Kingdom, commanding that no Lawyer should plead nor Iudge determine in any such Case; whereupon the Plaintiffs were sent home with double losse, (case thus unjustly in Charges) and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Threats for desiring justice; and their Solicitour forc'd to fly the Court for looking after the businesse. Was this honest deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? Was this an opening or obstructing of Law? Tell now, and call your selves Knaves. Ye are brave men to steer a State, Be ye not? The City and Kingdom both have known enough of such like seazures: but we shall straight finde a way to strip <hi>Aesops Mag-Pie</hi> out of her plundred Plumes.</p>
            <p>You made out many Ordinances that your under Officers should not wrong the Publique by vertue of any Act, Order or Ordinance of Parliament, or without Warrant, by Taxing, Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying, Collecting or Receiving; by Seizing, Selling, Disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing, or Disposing any Moneyes, Goods, Debts, Rents, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116375:8"/>of Friends or others, or by Setting or Letting to Frame De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquents Lands and Tithes. But you never held them to the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of such your Rules, nor punish any Frauds or Misde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanours in any such kind, though Iustice were required, but would send away the Plaintiffs (as you would have done the <hi>Warwickshire</hi> Gentry, had they not been so many and so earnest, as that you feared the revolt of that County) with threats be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daubing them with the norions of Malignancy, and desires to divide you amongst your selves: For whereas there was a great Subsidy granted about <hi>November,</hi> 1642. for the then pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent affaires of this Kingdome, and of <hi>Ireland:</hi> the one moity of the said Subsidie paid (at least in most places) by the severall Counties to Commissioners, according as the same Act appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; Neverthelesse there hath since Warrants issued forth (which are kept safe to be produced, if time once serve for such accusati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) signed with the proper hands of some of your Members, amongst the other your Committees, for the re-collecting of the said money paid before, and much more by colour of the said Act: And whereas you made an <hi>Ordinance,</hi> bearing date <hi>October</hi> the 16. 1644. for the supply of the <hi>British</hi> Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> ordering a weekly pay, to last for the space of a yeare, and the one moity of the assessement to be in Corne (at least in many places so) the other in moneyes; the same <hi>Ordinance</hi> was not put in executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on (I could tell you where) according to the tenor thereof; but about <hi>July,</hi> 1645. Warrants were sent out by some of your Members then in the Countries, and Counsels of Warre, for the raising of divers great summes of money amounting to more than twice so much as was limited by the said <hi>Ordinance;</hi> and immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately upon the former Collections, new Warrants sent abroad for vast summes to be paid weekly, without any Orders from you (and yet you neither can find any Law for your taxations) and in default of payment, our goods and chattels by violence (as well to the person as goods of the party) have been distrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, detained, and sold without speedy payment, according to the Collectors demands, with a Command to the high Sheriffe (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legated by him to the under Sheriff) not to grant any Replevyn for our goods and chattels so violently taken away, contrary to the liberty of the Subject, and the knowne Lawes and custome of this Kingdome.</p>
            <p>You talked of calling for accounts, and seemed to doe so; but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116375:8"/>we are certain that the revenewes of Delinquents estates would have defrayed all, or the greatest part of the charge of the warre, without any so great burthens to the Countrey as have been laid upon it, had they been faithfully and really disposed of to the best advantage, and benefit of the publique but you have all made up your accounts honestly, it must needs be so; and indeed where one thiefe must account before another, who thinkes any great discoveries will be made; but let me tell you (and I'le tell you truly) how accounts were made; you nominated Committees for examination (men as much in fault as the Accountants) who put their hands to all reckonings, as they were presented without looking, if they were just and straight or no; meet thus you tryed accounts, who may thinke that those broak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en-fortuned and beggerly knaves (of which sort of people for the most part your Officers consisted) could compasse such estates, as they have done in so short time, and bring in just and true ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts; I trow not man: nay your own accounts (if they were examined as they should be) would prove no juister then the others; else, how come you by all that money you have from time to time send beyond Sea; We remember how vehemently you startled and exclaimed, when some of our City would have had an account of the proposition Plate.</p>
            <p>You made an Ordinance, that your Sequestrators, and their under-Officers, the Collectors and prizers should occupie no se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>questred Farmes; but the most of them did hold very good de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>measnes of 2. or 3 hundred <hi>per annum,</hi> and payed not a penny rent to the use of the publick for them, neither wanted they their pay from other levies.</p>
            <p>You likewise made an an Ordinance, that they should sell Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lignants goods at the best rate for the advantage of the publick; but they have been suffered to take what they pleased to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves, and the rest they have sold to their Favourites many times for lesse then halfe so much as others would have given for them.</p>
            <p>You made an Ordinance that they should take no bribes, and yet neither they nor you would ever doe any curtesie, or act of distribitive Iustice without a bribe.</p>
            <p>There was (in many Cities, and Townes taken in) booties seized, better worth then two hundred thousand pounds in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and Plate, and Iewels, and houshold furniture, I could tell
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116375:9"/>you where, and yet your <hi>Committees,</hi> your <hi>Prisers</hi> and men that sould them have not been asham'd to say, <hi>They made but thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern thousand pounds</hi> of such vast Bootie, though it hath been pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely known they have had above nineteen thousand pounds in <hi>money</hi> and <hi>plate</hi> out of one house, and fifteen thousand pounds worth of one mans Goods out of another; but truly, how they should put things to the best, I cannot see, running the wayes they did; for they would first proclame a <hi>Day of Salt,</hi> to fetch in the Countrie <hi>Chapmen,</hi> and when they were come, put the day off again, to weiry them out of the Townes with expence, and then the non-fighting Officers would take the best and most of the prey unto themselves, besides selling <hi>Robbin Hoods</hi> penny worths for Bribes: this was the deportment of many of them. Ye should have summoned in the Countrey, and the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> to have shewed what <hi>money,</hi> and <hi>goods,</hi> and <hi>provision</hi> was fetched from them from time to time, and by whom, and have compared their notes with your Accountants, ye should have examined the Musters of your men, and so ye might have found out Receits, and guessed what Disbursements might have been; and this would soon have been done by many Officers, and many Divisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Countles. And who but such as are altogether void of honestie and shame would carry themselves thus unrighteously, or bear with it? These things ye could not chuse but know; for those of you that were abroad in the Warres were eye-witnesses of the same, and yet ye never minded to redresse them.</p>
            <p>After this manner have you ever looked to the publique Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, and no otherwise; besides it was usual with your <hi>Independent</hi> Faction (though no fighters) at taking of Townes to get Orders from <hi>Committes</hi> (by scraping legs and crouching) for <hi>Cavaliers</hi> houses, and then take goods, is all for their own use, without pay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of a penny for them to the Publique: this is not unknown to many: and as if you would leave no trickes unpractised by which you might beguile and abuse the Countrey; ye devised an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other tricke to get more of their monies: your Committees must lend ye, but what? The monies they have gathered from the Countrey by Loanes and Mizes, and the Countrey must pay eight <hi>per cent.</hi> interest for loan of the same. Thus do ye daily onely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult how to delude and abuse the Countrey; thus do ye continue your sitting for no other end, but that ye may sucke up the fat of the Kingdom, but ye shall see now it hath found your Knavery, it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116375:9"/>will shortly turne ye over another leafe, it hath provided a trap to catch your Foxes: ye cried out upon the <hi>King</hi> for heavy Taxes, which neverthelesse by your own computation amounted but to 700000. <hi>l per annum,</hi> in the whole thorow out the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Kingdom,</hi> which was no great Summe to build and maintain so many ships and Souldiers as his Majesty then had for the desence of his <hi>Kingdomes;</hi> and ye quarrelled the manner of his leavying such monies (forsooth) <hi>because there was no Statute law for the same;</hi> as if the <hi>pater patriae</hi> might not, where the Letter of the Law fals too short, make use of his own and his Counsels discre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for his Peoples preservation. O, but had he made you the Collectours, that you might have lick'd your fingers, as ye have done since ye put your selves into Offices, all had been well enough: but for the masse of money levied, if your Proposition money, your fifths and twentieth parts, your continual Loanes and Mizes, and your other innumerable Taxations, your Seque, strations of Goods and Lands, your plunder and pillage, your Souldiers Free-quarter, and provisions for your stores were or could be cast up, they would be found valuable to buy twenty times 700000. <hi>l. per annum.</hi> Thus have you good State-phisicians medicined our Diseases: yet we cannot deny you to be cunning Doctours, ye have kept our Purses so long in Phisicke. And I pray you, Had ye any president in the Law to imprison men un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>convicted of vice, and make them ransome themselves with great Summes of money, as ye did (when ye sent the Propositions tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the Countrey) those that refused to furnish you according to your demands? I trow not, ye know it is a breach of the Law, and an infringement of the <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> both which <hi>ye form sworne wretches</hi> swore to maintain. Ye accuse the <hi>King</hi> of neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting <hi>Ireland,</hi> and I o since the War was ended here, what care ye have taken to relieve it? ye have sent sometimes handfuls of men over to be cut off so soon as they came there: ye might as good have hang'd them here before they had gone, as sent them thither by such inconsiderable Companies. This is the great care ye take of those Plantations, and of this People of <hi>England.</hi> O, but now you'l mend in that point, ye are beating Drummes all over the Countries for Souldiers for <hi>Ireland,</hi> but the truth is, it is to retruit your Army here: ye mean to send them into the <hi>West</hi> to fight (you'l tell them when they come there) with <hi>Irish</hi> Rebels newly landed; ye have not men enough to spare hence; and <hi>if we should</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:116375:10"/>(sayes <hi>Cromwell</hi>) <hi>draw our Army off the City, it would follow us in the Rear, and being but such a handfull as we now be, they would cut us all off.</hi> We are in a pitifull case now, to stay or go we know not: stay, and the <hi>Scots</hi> and the Lord <hi>Inchiquinn</hi> come in upon us; go, and the Citie followes us. I smell a Rat, the blazing Comets are going out with a filthy stinke. An Ordinance of <hi>Parliament</hi> to passe four great ships without search laden with money, and now at <hi>Gravesend,</hi> or newly put to <hi>Sea.</hi> Nay, but your <hi>Souldiers</hi> a rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing are for <hi>Ireland,</hi> ye have a while ago made an Ordinance for the leavying of 20000 <hi>l. per moneth,</hi> for their maintenance: so ye made out before in <hi>August,</hi> 1644. for the promotion of that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, but the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> took 60000. <hi>l.</hi> of that money at <hi>Leicester: Dublin</hi> ye had not then: I pray ye, Was that the way to <hi>Corke</hi> and <hi>Kingsale,</hi> or <hi>Youghall?</hi> Ye fault the <hi>Cavaliers</hi> of <hi>Cheshire</hi> for stop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping some Cloathes bound for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and yet the Apparell given by those of the <hi>City</hi> for those Souldiers use was all (which was worth any thing) sold to the Brokers in <hi>Long-lane,</hi> onely a few ragges that would not make money here, were sent away. A man might here go farre enough to put ye out of your own practice, who, if ye had not so much honestie as to forbear ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumniating your Enemies, should have had so much diseretion as not to accuse another of that, which had ye had that good signe of a bad Cause in ye, <hi>blushing,</hi> might ashame ye, being by recrimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation retorted upon your selves. We have beard much your out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cries against <hi>the Whore of Babylon:</hi> and your charging (with much hitternesse and vehemencie) of her vices upon the <hi>See of Rome,</hi> and its Disciples, whose foot-steps ye trace in your fediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous courses; but if ye would look a little into the signification of the word, and into your selves and your proceedings: what <hi>Towers of Babel</hi> ye are erecting, what imaginations, what <hi>Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> and confusion ye are setting up, what Missives ye send abroad to broach all sorts of damned Heresies, those <hi>Locusts of the bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse pit, your gifted men</hi> as ye call them, your suppression of godly and learned Divines and their Escripts, and your countenancing and licencing any thing that favours of the <hi>Stygian</hi> Lake, ye would finde something reflecting upon your selves: the word <hi>Babel</hi> signifies <hi>confusion,</hi> and that which is chiefly observable of a <hi>Whore,</hi> is, <hi>her prostitution of her selfe to all,</hi> her wiles by which she enticeth her Lovers, and where with enticed she retaines them to her: now whether ye have not prostituted your selves unto all,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116375:10"/>let all <hi>England</hi> judge. In the beginning ye solicited by five or six several Letters Sir <hi>Arthur Aston,</hi> (a known <hi>Papist</hi>) before his Majesty entertained him, and yet you cried out against the <hi>King</hi> for accepting his Service. Ye sent five hundred <hi>Iewes</hi> (Enemies unto the <hi>Christian Faith</hi>) in your Armie to <hi>Newbery,</hi> there was a hundred of them slain upon the ground, known by the marke of <hi>Circumcision,</hi> ye have pleased and run on with the rude multitude the froathy scumme of the People in their worst and wickedest humours. Ye have suffered them to deface the earthly beautie of Gods earthly houses, to rend and tear in pieces our <hi>Common pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er-book,</hi> and the Priests Surplice, a badge of innocencie; to pull down Crosses, the proper Cognisance, by which the World might know to what Master this Kingdom did belong; and now at last ye invite men to deny the Master too; Ye countenance Atheists and Heretickes, and frown on them that defire to quell them; nay, ye fight with them, and kill them; ye have continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally during the whole time of the Warre (and since too, now ye might better have restrained them) suffered every <hi>Rapscallion</hi> (that bore Armes amongst you) to abuse and trample on (as he pleased) the Free-holders of the Countrey, to lord it over them, to beat and command them and their houses, where they quarter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or passed by: Rogues that before mended Pots and Kettles, or begd with butter-milke Kannes about the Countrey, must now call for roast, and beat all the house if it be not to be had: neither <hi>when such Grievances were made known unto you, Did ye curbe or checke the saucinesse of your Soaldiers herein, but rather deride the Plaintiffs?</hi> How stood (thinke ye) such abusings with the Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the <hi>English</hi> Farmers, and with the <hi>Kational Covenant and Protestation.</hi> And as a Whore hath ever her slights by which she inveagles her Lovers, so have ye had yours; as the <hi>Venetian Courtezans,</hi> at their first comming to the Citie to serve their Duke, send out a Crier through the streets to proclame their Beauties and the price thereof; so ye in the beginning of your Sessions sent abroad your <hi>Declarations</hi> in the specious notions of <hi>liberty, property,</hi> and <hi>priviledge;</hi> and the price, some <hi>proposition-money</hi> or some <hi>plate;</hi> and even as Whores, when they have drawn in silly <hi>Shallowlings,</hi> will ever finde some trick to retain them till they have brought them to a morsel of bread, especially if they doubt their starting, so have you still drawn our apprehensions off your perfidious. Actions, and kept our braines busied and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116375:11"/>with your Diurnalls and your Ordinances; which you have ever studyed for and set forth to this very end, not that which you expresse in the front of them, the satisfaction and right Information of the Kingdome: when you had discovered your cloven feet in <hi>August,</hi> and saw the peoples grumblings, you thought an Ordinance for making up accounts would be a piece of satisfaction for the present; and you knew the vulgars <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>raines retaine not long the phantasmes of things; but what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance was of that I have before in some part (as I could) shewed.</p>
            <p>You have moved rumors likewise oft times, and tell us again <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> every day of sending for the King, and setling the Kingdome, only to keep the people in suspence; and by vaine hopes of you, <gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o retard our endeavours for our own relief: by that you may still by disarming Townes get more power to continue your Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, now growing towards an end: for you never intend it, you are such notorious abominable Traitors, You have so much abus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Majesty, his late royall Mother, and his Royall Spouse, his Children, and us his people, that you dare not doe it; How oft of late have we heard, that <hi>Hampton</hi> Court hath been ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ready, and that <hi>Cromwell</hi> hath been gone to fetch him this day, and that, and the other; and it nothing so.</p>
            <p>Your diurnals buzz'd us in the eares with much good newes of many victories (lest we should have set from <hi>Dan</hi> and <hi>Bethel</hi> towards the Temple) even the first yeare of the warre, when our Armies went to wrack every where; and we had soon found it, had not our brethren of <hi>Scotland</hi> come in to our assistance: yet you send them (you say) to prevent misinformation: but when they began to speak against you (as after your taking away the <hi>Militia</hi> of this City of <hi>London,</hi> a thing I never heard nor read before, that any <hi>Parliament</hi> had to doe with all) they must be silenced till the peoples thoughts were drawn aside: we have been often slattered in the Countrey with casement of our Taxes, and free-quarter, if we would pay one small weekly payment, and quarter but a little longer: and loe presently you have sent (I am sure to many places of the Kingdome) for whole multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of vast summes, one in the neck of another, that we have almost nothing left: Thus have you in your Consultations, even from the beginning of your Sessions, even unto this vsry day, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vised nothing but how to delude and begger us all. and how to
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116375:11"/>keep warre on foot; else why accepted you not those many fair-offers of a gracious King, but still as you got more power in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croached both upon him and us, Why send you not for him home, but still delay us, 'tis not farre to him: We will study a way henceforth to ease our selves of such Magistrates, such sheen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clad wolves: It is not your going back to the Articles presented at <hi>Hampton Cours</hi> shall now make your attonement with us: You never took a way yet to make him a glorious King, or to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, but deforme Religion, or to settle us under our ancient Lawes, or in our native Liberties: had you power we know your minds; We give you no thanks for your pretending to settle <hi>Presbyterie,</hi> since you wanted power to hinder it; nor for your late Ordinance against Hereticks: put on your consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering Caps some what closer to your Cocks-combs, and see now if you can reingratiate your selves with our City: See if it will thanke you to transferre its <hi>Malitia,</hi> and Tower, (one of these in those they now be) into other <hi>Independents</hi> hands, and yet you did not that till very now: See if you can ingage your Brethren in the City, and us in a new warre, and we shall observe who be ready in the same; See if you can or dare force us <hi>Presbyterians</hi> or our apprentises to accompany you, and they shall carry away your weapons, and joyne with our friends your enemies: You must no more looke to force or mugle men with the name of a <hi>Parliament</hi> (being but a prevailing party,) and fill your Coffers by deceit: We will believe you no further; nor <hi>Fairfax,</hi> though he goes again to hear the Lord <hi>Primate</hi> preach at the <hi>Temple,</hi> or proclaime for King, or King and <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> Carry you the King captived along with you which way ere you goe: as strictly as you have watcht him, he hath given the Prince power to contract for him; We are got before-hand with you in that; Counterfeit his Seale, and make what Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations you will hereafter in his name, none shall believe you; We have been told the ends of your laying open <hi>Rochester:</hi> but if our Brethren of the Association, cannot get into a readinesse to stop your passage, the power of three Kingdomes shall shortly follow you.</p>
            <p>We heard of your late Designes against our City, before we took notice of them, and we hear your intentions are to proceed, and to draw up both <hi>Horse</hi> and <hi>Foot</hi> to atchieve the same. I saw some of their Leaders here the other day, and their men not farre
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116375:12"/>off, it is not denying and seeming to over-run your said Designes, shall make us negligent of our own safetie, if ye know not there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, Why do ye (to obstruct Discoveries) refer the Examination to men accused, <hi>viz. Ireton?</hi> How can you daub over this? or why, (if you set not on <hi>Fairfax</hi> in <hi>August</hi> last against our Citie) did ye go from the Houses to him? and why did ye not since vote him a Traitour, as ye did the Lord <hi>Inchiquin?</hi> My Brethren look over <hi>Diuruals,</hi> and ye shall see him ever acting in relation to the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses. Our Brethren of <hi>Essex</hi> came but peaceably with a Petition, and this prevailing party derides them gone, calling them <hi>Essex calves,</hi> but thankes to Face, yet delaies, that if they can quiet them a while, they may after make them the Spoil of the <hi>Iudepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> Army they declare against. Look to it Gentlemen, disperse not your selves till ye see it disbanded, and the King settled.</p>
            <p>Ye must ever have some cloke for your knaverie; when your late Designe against our <hi>City</hi> grew ripe, your Maior <hi>(a very Horse and a Traitour to our City, as many others of the common counsel and cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains be)</hi> must quarrell the Boyes at recreations, that ye might get another colour to draw your Army again upon the <hi>city,</hi> and do that which then ye durst not, <hi>get down our chaines,</hi> that when the time of your necessitie came, ye might disarme us, command our purses, and force us and our servants against our consciences, though now again ye are forc'd to pull in hornes; and bring ye up your County Souldiers (as we hear ye have) we shall make ye aking hearts yer ye obtain your wils: ye are loath to leave us; but (since we know your good will) well shall look to ye as we can: We trust our Brethren of the Association will be ready to assist us. We have heard now of your private compliance with <hi>Irish</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, and your Letters lately taken at Sea, wherein ye promite liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of conscience, and many immunities, if they will let ye alone. Thus have I given you a little sight of the <hi>Babylouian Bel</hi> like Idol, <hi>A brasen Parliament,</hi> and of the collusion and voracity of the <hi>Idol attendants, this prevailing party</hi> of both Houses, who have so long deluded ye with devices, and like <hi>Belt priests</hi> wasted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on themselves and theirs those vast Contributions and Leavies which should have been expended on the publique Service; and do desire (now time is like to serve for it) ye would endeavour your own freedom from the yoke of these men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God save the King and Kingdome.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>